Thank you everyone, thank you all
for coming to today's MagNetZ seminar
on behalf of the team we welcome you
again today. Our format usually is
about 30 minutes presentation and followed
by about 10 to 15 minutes time for Q&A
and you can write your questions in the chat or
unmute yourself and ask them. And then it's
going to be time for a catch up in the end
which is not recorded if you're interested
and I'm really happy to introduce you today to
Trond Torsvik from the University of Oslo Norway
who's going to present the mind-bending mystery
of the Hawaiian Emperor Bend. So thank you, the
floor is yours [Trond] I have to apologize I didn't read
the email very well I was I thought this was
like 45 minutes to an hour but then I was just
told it's 25 to 30 minutes I have to be very very
fast and so what I'm going to talk about is
something I was mostly interested in like four five
six years ago before the covid and this talk
I gave as a Friday seminar it's kind
of anonymized in a way. I'm talking about
some controversy, great debate but I'm trying
to anonymize it. I don't even show the reference to my
own work or other people except in the beginning.
It's really concerned with why do we
have this bend in the Emperor Hawaiian chain
and literally every paper you read on this issue
and introduction will state these pre-causes
either it’s an abrupt Pacific Plate motion change
at around 47 million [years ago], rapid southward drift of the
Hawaiian hotspot before 47 million indicated by
this cell or a combination of these two causes.
And for a long time, I was
kind of tempted to go for a combination but
the more I thought about trying to understand the
bend I think the bend itself is not a combination
but probably actually by plate motion change. But
still we cannot ignore the effect of hotspot drift.
This debate, as many others, is characterized
by scientific polarization. Contemporary societies
are often polarized in the sense that subgroups within
these society hold stably opposing beliefs and
then they write: even when there is a fact of the
matter. The problem is what we consider ‘the fact
of the matter’ so people actually do research into
this. And there are many polarized debates we have.
We have Pangea A versus Pangea B, it's a classic
one. We have plate versus plumes as another
one. I prefer to say plates and plumes because
I do believe in plumes and I do believe in plate
tectonics and of course we have very different
opinions on how this model works in deep Earth.
We also have, many of you are probably aware of,
we have these low velocity zones in the lowermost
mantle beneath Africa and the Pacific. Some
argue they are stable, partly because when you
reconstruct a large igneous province through time
they have a tendency of forming along the margins.
The only real exception is Columbia River Basalt
and this is for the last 300 million years. But then you
have others, who think there are dynamic LLSVPs and
they're just pushed around by subduction zones
which you see as white lines here. And of course
in modelling there is, this is from actually from a
Nature paper from this year and I just picked one
of them, the one they prefer, model 7 out of 22.
So stable versus dynamic LLSVPs. And
what I'm going to talk about today,
which is kind of polarized, hotspot motion
version plate motion change. But part of the
discussion also is: are the hotspots
fixed or moving? Some actually have
some of them, only the Pacific, moving and the
Indo-Atlantic [hotspots] are fixed so that's another version.
And here you can see I anonymized these, it’s the
paper from 2017, 2019 they've totally different
Opinions. Pacific plate motion change caused the
Hawaiian-Emperor Bend which was here at about 47 [Ma].
And the other one, two years later, Hotspot motion
caused… and they said: and
LLSVP are not fixed. So they are dynamic and moved.
So that was added on. But you can see here it is
clearly two very different and
polarized opinion on this matter. In this debate we
also have a problem ‘what are the plate circuits?’
How do you link to Pacific to Indo-Atlantic?
And also a discussion on True Polar Wander,
if that is something making trouble here, or not?
Just a few things about the Hawaiian-Emperor Bend, it was
first suggested by Tuzo Wilson 1963,
that you actually had a what they call a focused spot
of melting in the mantle which produced the Hawaiian
chain. This was later termed hotspot, Jason Morgan
in 1971 who also proposed these hotspots are sourced
by deep mantle plumes. Morgan also was first in
building the first kinematic model to define absolute
plate motion in a fixed hotspot
reference frame and of course
In this model, we talk about 1972, the Hawaiian
Emperor Bend was attributed to a change in the
absolute motion of the Pacific Plate. So that
was in 1972. And there are there's a number of
problems with this fixed hotspot, it doesn't really
work very well but I will not dwell on that here.
But it’s just interesting, 45 years later – 2017, one
group actually has exactly the same conclusion.
And actually some people reacted to this paper and
said ‘what's new?’ Morgan said it already in 1972 so
here you have one group actually following.
Another problem with explaining
that it was actually a plate motion change was
pointed out by Ian Norton. He called it the
43 million non-event. We now have it about 47
million years [ago]. He said such a large and abrupt
direction change -about 60 degrees- should result
in significant plate reorganization and tectonic
events in the Pacific and surrounding plates. But no evidence
for these can be found. I would disagree today,
but at that time that was a valid argument and
um so he said it must be a non-stationary hotspot.
So the other paper from 2019, 25 years
Later, kind of agrees with Ian Norton on this.
But of course I'm a paleomagnetist and this is a MagNetZ
Seminar, although it won't be too much about paleomag, but
of course paleomag was very important
in this debate in early time and and
if you look at the oldest Detroit seamount
you can see if you plot them with Hawaii
Fixed, this is about 19 degrees at the moment, but
it just put fixed at zero, you could see the Detroit
plotted about 15 degrees to the north. And it
looks like a nice [trend], coming down and the Bend is
about here at 47 [Ma]. So I thought this was a pretty cool
and important paper for many many years.
But some these things got me
a little curious. It would be nice because from the
Paleomag, if you start sampling young enough it
should fall on the zero line you know, if the Bend
was purely related to this issue but if you actually
looked at a younger one and there was an old Midway
basalt about here, but now there’s a new one
just for the basalt but they actually average
soils and basalt and got us almost at zero- the
correct answer. But still we have a problem with
Hawaii that doesn't fit and also Oahu, or how you pronounce
it. So there still seems to be an inclination and
latitudinal anomaly even with the youngest. So
that concerned me a little about apparent date [age].
And if you do a True Polar Wonder
Correction, and there’s of course a different way of doing
This, I'm doing it the way I do it. You see actually
only Detroit actually falls above the zero line
or Hawaii fixed. And it's about nine degrees and
all the others are below so I was a little
confused with whether this actually works or is
there something wrong with the True Polar Wander
Correction? Also there’s written a paper trying to
understand is anomaly here was caused by
A non-dipole field and we have these Low Velocity
Zones at the core-mantle boundary and Hawaii is sitting
on the margin and some would say you would have
strong variations in core-mantle boundary heat flow
which could lead to non-dipole field contributions.
And people also say that for instance by the
Reunion [hotspot] but we have resampled the Reunion and we don't
actually find this anomaly there any longer. When
it comes to True Polar Wander, I think it's quite easy
to explain it from, we have a phase from 200 to 150 [Ma],
you can see all the continents are rotating on a
point which is close to the equator, about 11 degrees.
You see a similar [thing] 150 to 140 [Ma], 100 to 110 [Ma], when it comes
to the younger parts and you can see it in here, for
the younger part will actually use the difference
from a hotspot reference frame and actually at
the critical time and it's 200 to 130 and back
here and maybe for the last 40 million years you
are actually rotating on an axis which is close to
this point at around 10-11 degree but you can see
there is something funny going on from about 90
to 40 [Ma], and this is in a critical period
where we also try to do True Polar Wander correction
for the paleomagnetic data on the Hawaiian chain.
You can also see the speed of True Polar Wander we
get from these models and even today, today True
Polar Wander is something happening right now. We can
measure that you geodetically it’s happening about
at one degree per million year or 10 centimeter
per year but from these models we only got
like 0.35 or something and the difference here
actually could be partly deglaciations. Actually
global warming that actually contributes to True
Polar wander today. And of course modeling since 2016
people also tried to do. So we had this with the
paleomag and also from modelling. There's a
paper in Nature 2016: A rapid burst in hotspot
motion through the interaction of tectonics and
deep mantle flow and they have a statement here:
“rapid hotspot motion of the Hawaiian plume followed by
a sharp..” I would- one of the messages I gave you -
I should say- it was all southward and mentioned my
word southward or something close to southward.
The main message in the end I would say, that's
impossible from a geometrical point of view.
That would be an important point of this lecture.
So I just show this, this was from
a model point of view and in their model
they actually took just the Jason, one of these
low velocity zones now and it's actually pushed
Southward. And if you look at the model hotspot
drift so this is the southward you can see it's
about 12 degrees here it goes down and it
flattens out a little just before the Bend
But of course the ideal scenario would
be go down there if that was all.
The immediate problem you see with this conclusion
is that this is only nine degrees, but the Emperor
Chain is actually 19 degrees so everyone with
simple mathematics would realize you are missing 10
degrees here. So you just by looking at this simple
geometry you realize there is something wrong.
Also you can look at different tomography
models and you can advect it back in time
and you can compare them. Here, this was a
forward model, the one I wanted to point it out you can
take a number of backward advected
models here. You probably know about Smean,
Savani, this is one of the newest, Semucb. The
message from this is that none of these models actually
see anything special happening they go straight
through at that time and too little to account for
the length. You see there's about 10 to 12 degrees so
none of these really show anything spectacular if
you believe in models. So now it's really the
lecture, and I was very fast because that speed
was supposed to be very slow and
gave you a really cool introduction.
So we have to understand
this thing: what's the effect of
hotspot drift and what's the effect of plate motion?
When I was sitting on a balcony in Berlin
in 2016 had a lot of red wine on my
my sabbatical there, and thought there must be some way of
figuring out what is possible and not possible with
all these things. Because there is a
lot of variables and we can't all be right
or wrong. So I'll start with a popular claim:
the Emperor seamounts were formed by rapid
southward motion of the Hawaiian hotspot between 81
and 47 million years [ago] so that's this thing here. Okay,
to do that, if it's southward, you need 19 degrees. And
in this very simple simulation we attribute the
entire north-south length (19°) to southward hotspot drift
over this interval and we assume that the Pacific
Plate moved with the same angle of velocity before
and after the formation of the Bend. That's
about 0.72 degree per million years so that's the
Assumption. If you try to do some arithmetics on
this you will see in this scenario the hotspot
Would have to move so fast, actually five times faster than the
Pacific Plate, at a rate of 3.8 degrees per million
years. So this is the rate you need to do it. And if
you look at this number now, in order to do that,
this extremely fast motion implies that the entire
Emperor chain was created in just five million years, okay?
So then you get an understanding that this
is geometrically impossible because we know
that this [the Detroit Seamount] should be 80 and not 52 million years old.
So geometrically you cannot state that you
can explain the Bend by southward drift. It is to
my understanding of Euler geometry not
possible. So here you can show it
with the time, it is just an animation. This would
be actually the ages of the Emperor and Hawaii
Chain if it was purely [explained] by southward hotspot drift.
And if you make it even slightly more aligned
with Emperor chain you need even to do it faster.
We can do another simulation, you can
actually get a fit to the ages, but you
can only do that if you move the Pacific Plate
before the Bend at an extremely low rate, okay?
So you have to move it really really tiny to be
able to get a hotspot drift down to let's say
0.58 degree per million. So I guess this example
requires an extremely slow rate of
0.13 followed by a nearly sixfold acceleration after
47 Ma, which is not supported by any observational
Model. But be aware this is also a change in plate
Motion, but it's a change in plate velocity, okay?
So it's highly unlikely.
So a simple consideration shows that it would be extremely
difficult, I'd say extremely, almost theoretically
impossible to reproduce the HEB if no change occurred.
Okay as I'm saying that, but it's a kind of easy
conclusion out of this geometrical exercise, but
can it be demonstrated that plate motion change is actually the
cause for the HEB? Do we actually have models
where we actually get this to fit? I’ve now told
you what is not possible and now we have to have
some way of fitting these things. For that we need
absolute plate motion frames and for the last
130 million years we can use a mixture of moving
and fixed hotspot Global reference frames and we are
only really concerned with the last 80 million
years and this has been done. One of the first
one of these is from 2004 and this
paper also pointed out some of the problems people
had for a decade or two, that if you assume that
Africa hotspots were fixed. Sorry if all hotspots
were fixed, you will see this stippled line there you
cannot reproduce that Emperor Chain. And
this one is kind of weird because it's had the Africa
hotspot fixed and the Hawaii hotspot moving and
I think the reason this curve was introduced is
because there are actually some people claiming
that the African or Indo-Atlantic [hotspots] are
actually fixed, and only the Pacific [hotspots] are moving.
But still you can’t really see much, maybe a
little Bend there and in this particular paper it
also had to do with different plate circuits again
a Model A now you can see you start reproducing
the Emperor chain but in this favorite model in
this paper model B you can see it's not too bad
up to about 60 million years. But then it sets off.
That was in 2004, there was a new model,
there's another one in 2008 now you can see it's
the same as model B but with some modification
on some plate circuits, etc. You can see we can kind
of reproduce that the Emperor path as well
To show the latest models, actually 10 years
Old, so it's timely to build another one, but
I just show you the 2012 version. What’s it based
On? It’s based on using five hotspot tracks and
here's the Hawaii Emperor, it’s one of them they
are fitted with spherical spline fits. You
put on relative plate circuits and then
you backward advection of present-day mantle
density structure and of course there you use-
I have had to use a particularly a tomography
model this time we used the Smean
model but of course there are many others
out there it will give you slightly different
answers. But in this one for instance the Hawaii
for the younger part is southward. You can
see New England here, Reunion, Louisville has
much of an East-West variation and then
Tristan. So this is the Earth at 30
million years [ago] with five hotspots. The previous
version only had four hotspots so this was five.
And what do you get with this model? So this
was the 2008 model you can see in this latest
model here now you're pretty much able to
reproduce these things within the errors which is
really errors on ages and not very much more.
But you can see now we are able to reproduce
it. But of course what you are looking at there
is a combination of the plate motion and
hotspot drift. And to separate it out, to take away
now- we all know in the Pacific frame if
you now take away that hotspot drift to see
what is left it's like treating Hawaii in the
fixed hotspot reference frame, you actually see
what the plate motion is. So that's the red line.
And now you can see here the entire Bend.
So this is the real plate motion line in this.
So we are actually able to
reproduce this bend as a plate motion change.
But now you can see there's a missing part here,
it doesn't really reach up to Detroit and this,
what is missing there, that is the hotspot drift.
So again the entire 60 degree Hawaiian chain can be
explained by a change in Pacific plate motions. We
have shown that that is impossible theoretically
with a pure Southward drift model. But the hotspot
track that would be produced by it, it's mostly shifted to
the south it's north
running segment is about 800 kilometers shorter.
So you have a missing 800 kilometers. That is the
southward hotspot drift. To make a very simple
model, in this particular one we have a
a hotspot drift from 80 million years here
this is the real plate motion change, and the
missing part, 800 kilometers, is the hotspot drift.
So the take-home message is: explaining
everything by a southward drifting hotspot is
I call it a challenge. You know I said
impossible before but there is one way away
from this: that we have dated the rocks
wrong, you know they're not 80 [Ma] but they're
52 [Ma] but I doubt that. Somebody maybe didn't
get a decay constant right but I seriously
doubt that, so this is why I call it challenging
and also this scenario here where the plate
moved extremely slowly in order to get the age
progression right is a highly unlikely scenario.
You can do another one and in this process many
years ago I realized people have said this and
I think they even saw a diagram of somebody.
Because everyone talked about southward drift so
it's almost parallel to the
Hawaiian but of course you you can get away with it
it if the hotspot drift has this huge westerly
component okay. So then you can actually do this.
One of the problems with that is that if
you look at all geodynamic modelling, if you
believe in them. But if you believe in them
none of them actually show this kind of
Trend. They are either north to south or north-north-west to
south-south-east but again you can say if you
don't believe in geodynamic modelling you can
go for this one and um that is a possibility.
Just to be controversial towards the end decades of
debating hotspot drifts and plate motion change may have
been avoided if Leonhard Euler had all that
information in the 18th century since there are
simple Euler geometric considerations that must
be accounted for. And I hope that is factual
Information. Because we have ages, we have the
geometry, if there was a pure southward drift
we know it’d have to be 19 degrees you have a little
triangle here and and if we have the same speed
going here 0.72 per million years, we
get it we get into trouble because you have to
have a drift which is 3.8 degree per million
year I told you that before and the implication
is that the greater Emperor chain [would form] in five
million years and not 33 million years. So
Conclusion: hotspot motion ánd. There's a
lot of this debate. is something worse is something
else like plume versus plates. Many times you
can say you know plumes ánd plates or plates and
lumes. And it is also hotspot motion ánd plate
motion change but what I, at least for now, kind
of believe in, hotspot motion is simply the added
length of the chain or the Emperor chain
part and it’s the plate motion change which creates
the Bend. So here's the critical word 'and'
But of course but what caused
the plate motion change and to model that is another
Lecture. I could have given a lecture on that because
how do we go around this paper, what is this
non-event? But we have ideas for that in
some sort of old classic model. If you look in
the Pacific we have an Izanagi plate. It's
truly synthetic, so it means it's fully made up.
The Kula [plate] is kind of made up but it's you have the
counter under the Pacific it seems like some
sort of simple saying that there is not much going on
but actually if you look at tomography today it's
not only the Kula [plate] we can see here, very strong
in a tomographic model. We can call a North Pacific
Plate and there's a lot of arcs out there there's
paleomag on these, they get accreted.
The main thing here is a very big change
in the northern part of the Pacific just prior
to, and during, the Bend. And you can even see it in
a vertical section. Actually most of most of the
active ongoing subduction in both the
North and the West Pacific are actually
almost at Bend time initiated. And you can see it
beautiful here, with a slab
here, the Aleutian slab which you can see all
the way from the surface down to the transition zone
here. And I would say that is less, or equal
to HEB-time and you can in the in the bottom
here you actually find a pre-HEB which was this
part here which is now seen at 66 million years.
So I just hope, I have no idea about
my time, but thank you for your attention.
Thank you. [Anita] thank you very much Trond. Let's give
a big round of applause, thank you very much.
So we have time for questions
Many applause applauses thank you again
Anybody who wants to ask questions,
you can unmute yourself or you can write
in the chat and I will read it out.
[Vadim Kravchinski, Canada] May I ask a question?
[Anita]
Sure you're welcome
[Vadim] Hi Trond, thank you very much for such an
interesting presentation and are there any
other hotspots which also bend kind of
the same way and which existed for a very long
time so you could check if models you suggest
also work in other parts of the world? Like
Reunion for example existed for a long time
and some other in India some other hotspots in
the Indian Ocean did someone try this? Thank you
[Trond] well I was saying in the slide in the beginning
that Hawaii Emperor is really a remarkable unique feature
on Earth and there is nothing which is so long
lived and shows this sharp Bend and we have looked
at others, you mentioned Reunion, the Reunion at
least we think only lasts back to about 66
million years and we have
written about there is kind of a big change during
the acceleration of the of the Indian plate
it seems to be deflected kind of what's going
to be northeastward and when the speed goes
down again it kind of comes back again so but
but the Hawaii Emperor Bend is really
really unique so it's very very hard to find any
good things like that unfortunately
it would be nice if we had many of them.
[who] thank you [Anita] thank you
any other question from the audience
[Rory] I've got one [Anita] you're welcome
[Rory] why must the Pacific Plate move during the
the Eocene why can't it be stationary or at
a standstill as it was during much of the mid
Cretaceous [Trond] Oh you mean just before the band yeah
well I'm saying it’s possible okay, but it is
possible, but then you also introduced and is
also changing you know when you do a change in
plate motion that could in in plate motion you
know as either the speed or the direction so
it's still that is a possibility but that is
it's really really slow you know and it doesn't
really fit in the global hotspot reference
frame that doesn't really fit okay unless
you ignore them but I don't believe in that
but it I I that is in one of the simulations
I showed you one possibility but it's
is not the change in in plate direction but
it's an extreme change in plate speed and yes
we had a still stand which was earlier but to
still stand you you're more thinking in terms of
magnetic and paleomagnetic poles okay and still
stand yeah and of course there was no North
America wasn't in still stand it was simply moving
uh westward okay is simply you had no you had no
change in the inclination data so it looks like
it's just an apparent so the North American still
stand and of course it's kind of disconnected
not disconnected connected to Pacific Plate so
that also means the Pacific Plate is moving uh
cannot also moves but the still stand is simply
simply that North America is not moving in
north-south at all so it's a paleomagnetic thing
[Rory] but the Pacific may not have also I mean there's
there are some paleomagnetic poles for the same
time they're based on marine magnetic
anomalies as well but they also suggest
that there was very little
motion of the Pacific Plate yeah
throughout much of the Eocene
[Trond] yeah that's true we also we also have looked at
the paleomagnetic poles but of course again in
this discussion it depends what data you look at
and uh and are you thinking about the one
derived from the skewed magnetic anomalies or
[Rory] there's yeah there there's a number there's um
uh a lot of of Gordon Acton's work through uh
uh 33R yeah which is based off of uh an
abstract only um we tried to do a azimuthally
reoriented pole for Detroit using the Brunhes
overprint to get a Detroit pole as opposed to
just looking at the paleolatitude data yeah
out and the paleolatitude of *what a chibito*
matches that of the Detroit colatitude um
let's see 27R also plots fine in the Pacific
so there's reason to believe the Pacific plate
itself similar to what it may have also been
doing during the middle Cretaceous is that it
was the Pacific Basin was more dominated by
the plates on its outside the Farallon plate
or the *cooler* plate or the Izanagi plate
the Pacific Plate wasn't moving there
was maybe asymmetric spreading the full
the Farallon plate that's uh there's one of the
conclusions that right um oh what year was that
2015. I I don't remember exactly but they were
looking at the fracture patterns as an example
for uh Pacific Farallon motion versus Pacific and
Antarctic motion and came up with and came
to the conclusion that there's no evidence of
a change in plate motion at 47 million years
based on looking at the fracture patterns within
the among other things but the fraction patterns
is what sits in my head uh and that the conclusion
was Pacific wasn't necessarily moving but most of
that motion was accommodated by the Farallon plate
moving to the east so why can't the Pacific Plate
simply be standing still [Trond] no no I'm not saying
this is theoretical impossible I think with my three
simulation the main point I want to make if you
just have southward hotspot drift which is that
is geometrically impossible okay yes that's the
only thing okay then you have two other options you
can either have almost a still stand and that's
what you're saying so if we can find some good
evidence for that but so that's theoretically
possible or that the plate drift had such a
um South westerly component so so what I try to
do it it's more some sort of feel I have been
thinking about this also you know was it this and
that and and it drove me nuts several papers and a
few years later I was wondering it was right and
wrong and I put myself on plate people with others
and suddenly I thought there must be some way at
least to put the boundary condition that's what
I try it's simple geometry what is possible okay
and maybe we should ask us that question sometimes
before we spend a lot of money trying to explore
something you know you know what is possible okay
like one paper there which is which is a
big headline in Nature using the biggest
supercomputer in the country I'm not going
to mention end up with a conclusion that
it's all due to southward drift okay which is
impossible. Right so you have a supercomputer
you know doing calculation for months coming
giving you something which is theoretically
impossible okay because that supercomputer is
not obviously wasn't trained in Euler geometry
you know, whether it just made sense or not and I
think that has to soften it makes me a little
sad seeing these kind of studies yeah so read
Nature if you're going to find something weird
it's a lot of it maybe in Science this one but
they they like sensations you see all right
when I try to publish this once upon a time in
the real nature it as this is not very interesting
and when I recover I'd say about it we have some
theoretical consideration a lot of these papers
you've published recently they're incorrect and
then they told me you can write a comment down but
I don't write comments you never win in comment
okay right the authors always have the last word
[Rory] Alright thank you I would like to thank you
again Trond for a very good presentation thank
you I'm really sure everybody enjoyed and
is always good to keep the dialogue and the
science going it's very lively and good I think
thank you very much again big round of applause
and I will share just the final slides
so uh we are keeping the EU America's time slot
until the the end of this year next talk is
going to be by James Bryson fifth of October
then uh Geoff Lerner from from Mexico and we're
gonna have other few talks so stay tuned in our
channels and we are looking for 2023 speakers
and you can find this recording and all
the previous ones on our YouTube channel so
stay up to date and follow us and thank you a lot
for for being here and following us thank you